William Tipping Papers, 1688-2001: Finding Aid
Princeton University Library. Department of Rare Books and Special Collections.
William Tipping Papers
1688-2001
C1462
Princeton University. Library. Dept. of Rare Books and Special Collections Manuscripts Division One Washington Road Princeton, New Jersey 08544 USA
2.4 linear feet 3 archival boxes, 1 oversize box
Tipping, William.
Conists of personal papers of William Tipping Esq, of Brasted Park, Sevenoaks, in Kent, and Avray near Paris. He was the son of the successful Liverpool merchant John Tipping, who in his twenties traveled extensively in Europe and the Middle East before turning to Tory politics and serving as director of the London and North Western Railway.
William Tipping Esq, of Brasted Park, Sevenoaks, in Kent, and Avray near Paris, was the only child of the successful Liverpool merchant John John Tipping Esq. of Liverpool. He married, in 1844, Maria, daughter of Benjamin Walker Esq. of Leeds. He travelled extensively in Europe and the Middle East when in his twenties before turning to Tory politics and serving as director of the London and North Western Railway. He was a Justice of the Peace for Kent, for Lancashire, and for the West Riding of Yorkshire, and Member of Parliament for Stockport 1868 1874, and 1885 1886. He was a Director of the North Western Railway. http://armorial.library.utoronto.ca/stamp-owners/TIP001
Includes a series of approximately one hundred and forty family letters, comprising some 450 pages, written on tours of Europe and the Middle East around 1840, several charmingly illustrated. Includes a copious run of retained drafts of letters to Isaac Taylor, the publishers Houlston & Wright, Dr. Robert Traill, the painter Josiah Gilbert, and others, concerning publication of plates after drawings made on his tours, as well as a quantity of additional family material (manuscripts, letters, books, 1777-1960s and beyond). Also includes a signed portrait of William Tipping. There are is also a quantity of additional family material, such as manuscripts, letters, photographs, brochures, books, and periodicals dated 1777-1960s and beyond.
This collection has been organized into the following series:
The collection is open for research.
Purchased in 2013.
Nothing was removed from the collection.
The following printed maps have been transferred to the Historic Maps Collection: 1.Map of the Peninsula of Mount Sinai and Arabia Petraea from the itineraries of E. Robinson and E. Smith constructed and drawn by H. Kiepert, Berlin 1841. Published as the act directs by John Murray. 50 Albermale Str. London. April 1841. (HMC01.7067). 2. Die Insel St. Helena, [circa 1822-1840]. (HMC01.7070). 3. Konigreich Griechenland (Kingdom of Greece), nach den neuesten und besten Hulfsmitteln, entworfen und gezeichnet von C.F. Weiland. 1833. (HMC01.7069). 4. Plan of Jerusalem, sketched from Sieber and Catherwood, corrected by the Measurements of Robinson and Smith. Drawn by H. Kiepert. Published as the act directs by John Murray. 50 Albermale Str. London. April 1841. (HMC01.7068).
Houlston and Wright.; Ottewill, David; Manuscripts, English -- New Jersey -- Princeton.; Correspondence -- 18th century.; Correspondence -- 19th century.; Correspondence -- 20th century.; Diaries -- 19th century; Manuscripts, English -- 19th-century.; Manuscripts, English -- 20th century.; Photographic postcards.; Photographs.; Hellenic studies
- Series 1. Correspondence, 1755-1988; more than 13 folders
  This series consists of approximately one hundred and forty family letters, comprising some 450 pages, written on tours of Europe and the Middle East around 1840, several nicely illustrated. Includes a copius run of retained drafts of letters to Isaac Taylor, the publishers Houlston and Wright, Dr. Robert Trail, the painter Josiah Gilbert, and others, concerning publication of plates after drawings made on his tours. The present letters - many of which, written on large extended sheets of paper, are very long - display the élan of a young Englishman on the Grand Tour and provide the reader with a vivid view of Middle Eastern travel in the first half of the nineteenth century.
  This series has been arranged in an alphabetical order.
  - Mollet, John S., 1834-1835; 1 folder (Folder 1)
    Includes incoming correspondence from John S. Mollet to John Tipping.
  - Ottewill, David, 1988; 1 folder (Folder 2)
    Includes correspondence between David Ottewill and Gordon Singleton.
  - Tipping, John, 1816-1835; 1 folder (Folder 3)
    Includes outgoing correspondence to his wife and his brother, Joseph Fearon.
  - Tipping, John, 1841-1853; 1 folder (Folder 4)
    Includes outgoing correspondence to his friend, Isaac Taylor; one letter to James Lester; and one letter to his son William.
  - Tipping, Joseph Fearon, 1834-1835; 1 folder (Folder 5)
    Includes outgoing correspondence to his brother John Tipping.
  - Tipping, William, 1834-1836; 4 folders (Folder 6-9)
    Includes outgoing correspondence from William Tipping to his father John and three letters to his uncle, Joseph Fearon. There are also contemporary handwritten copies of letters that were composed by William Tipping (see folder 7).
  - Tipping, William, 1837-1838; 1 folder (Folder 10)
    Includes outgoing correspondence from William Tipping to his father John. There is also one letter from John S. Mollet.
  - Tipping, William, 1839; 1 folder (Folder 11)
    Includes outgoing correspondence from William Tipping to his father, John Tipping.
  - Tipping, William, 1840-1843; 1 folder (Folder 12)
    Includes outgoing correspondence from William Tipping to his father, John Tipping. At the end, there are a few undated letters.
  - Tipping, William, 1841-1848; 1 folder (Folder 13)
    Includes outgoing correspondence to Isaac Taylor. The majority of the letters is undated.
  - Tipping, William, 1847; 1 folder (Folder 14)
    Includes undated letters written by William Tipping to Gilbert (probably the painter Josiah Gilbert) and one letter to the publisher Houlston and Wright (June 13, 1847).
  - Miscellaneous, 1755-1854; 1 folder (Folder 15)
    Consists of correspondence among family members, including letters from Mary Tipping, Thomas Tipping, and Jane Fearon to William Tipping; one letter from William Tipping to his mother; one letter from Fearon Tipping to his grandfather; two letters from John W. Tipping to his grandfather and to his uncle; one letter from Jane Fearon to Joseph Fearon and one letter from A. Tipping to John Tipping.
  - Miscellaneous, 1821-1978; 1 folder (Folder 16)
    Includes correspondence between William Tipping and Edward Ford; one letter from Edward Ford to Isaac Taylor; one letter form William Tipping to Griffith; one letter from J. Holmes to John Tipping; one letter to John tipping fromn his cousin Th. Bewley (?); one letter from grandmother Fearon to Jane; two letters from unidentified senders (one in French); one letter from Anthony Titley to William Tipping (July 9, 1866); one letter from Henry Avaray Tipping to Joan (26.7.1921); a few letters sent to William Tipping from unidentified senders; one letter in Arabic.
- Series 2. Writings, 1859-2001; 5 folders
  This series consists of autograph manuscript drafts and notes regarding the history of Tipping family, William Tipping's trips to the Middle East, and one bound manuscript diary of a tour in South America.
  This series has been arranged in a chronological order.
  - Manuscript Diary, 1859 March 24; 1 folder (Folder 1)
    Includes loose pages of a manuscript diary of a trip in the Middle East with mentions to Lebanon, Damascus, Kuwait, and Libya taken by an unknown author in 1859. The whole manuscript appears to have been written at the same time and with the same pen on blue paper, one must assume that it was created by Timming from earlier diaries (letters) and notes he kept on the trips. Inscription on first page reads: "Westerham - 24 March 1859".
  - South America Tour, 1925-1926; 1 folder (Folder 2)
    Includes a bound manuscript diary of a tour in South America from Decemeber 23, 1925 to April 4, 1926.
  - "The English Garden Abroad", 1998-2001; 1 folder (Folder 3)
    Includes an autograph manuscript of the above article prepared by Charles Quest-Ritson and published by Penguin Books in 1992. There are also miscellaneous notes.
  - William Tipping of Brasted: A Victorian Squire, undated; 1 folder (Folder 4)
    Includes contemporary autograph manuscript drafts of history of the Tipping family in pen and pencil. There is also a reproduction of a letter that was written by John Tipping on January 8, 1853.
  - Memorials of the Blaxland Family, undated; 1 folder (Folder 5)
    Includes contemporary autograph manuscript drafts in pencil.
- Series 3. Documents, 1688-1980; 7 folders
  This series consists of several legal documents, such as wills, deeds, mortgage, and certification of members of the Tipping family.
  This series has been arranged by type of material.
  - Will of Sir Thomas Tipping of Wheatfield, 1688-1972; 1 folder (Folder 6)
    Includes the original will of Sir Thomas Tipping, nephew of William Tipping. There is also a handwritten contemporary copy of the Will dated 1972.
  - Will of James Blaxland, 1710; 1 folder (Folder 7)
    Includes an original copy extracted from the Registry of the Consistory Court of Canterbury.
  - Will of John Tipping, 1822; 1 folder (Folder 8)
  - Wills of William Tipping and Maria Tipping, 1837-1980; 1 folder (Folder 9)
    Includes contemporary autograph drafts of the will of William Tipping, photocopies of the original will, and probate copies. There is also a copy of the will of Maria Tipping of Brasted Park, wife of William Tipping Esquire; a letter from the Cheshire County Council dated August 15, 1952 and one letter from the District Probate Registry to H.G. Singleton Esq. regarding William Tipping's will.
    Included also is an affirmation signed by William Tipping dated 1837.
  - Copy of Tipping's Deed at the Society of Genealogists, 1697; 1 folder (Folder 10)
  - Papers Relating to John Tipping of Skipton and William Tipping, 1748-1859; 1 folder (Folder 11)
    Includes an indenture between William Tipping and John Tipping dated 1748 (has been transferred to oversize Box 4, folder 3); one indenture between John Tipping of Skipton and John Birkbeck et al. (1843); a letter from Lowndes, Bateson and Co. to John Tipping in reference to his inquiry on his will; a certification that William Tipping took duty in her Majesty's High Court of Chancery; correspondence; and two lists of hotel expenses in Rome. In addition, there are autograph manuscripts regarding the genealogical tree of William Tipping and related information of other family members; a birth certificate of William Tipping; one passport of John Tipping in French dated 1841-1842 and a few other documents (see oversize Box 4, folder 3).
  - Miscellaneous, 1718-1841; 1 folder (Folder 12)
    Includes one firman issued by Negib Pasha in Arabic script dated 1841; one document signed by Alice Wright dated 1803; one document signed by John Lanyon; and a few pages of a notebook dated 1718.
- Series 4. Photographs and Postcards, 1835; 2 boxes (1 partial)
  This series consists of photographs and postcards of William Tipping and other literary figures or artists of the era.
  - Tipping Memorial at Stokenchurch Brasted, undated; 1 folder (Folder 1)
    Included also is an undated photograph probably of a trip in Egypt (105 x 65 mm) and one photograph of a coat of arms (178 x 125 mm).
  - William Tipping Portrait, 1835; 2 folders (Folder 1-2)
    Includes a signed portrait of William Tipping (dated 17 Aug./22 Dec. [18]35), attributed to the Saxon portraitist E[rnst] Oertel (1804-69), "Presented to me by Hofrat Emil Pestel of the Koerner Museum Dresden 9/1/99 / W.I.T.". Charcoal on toned paper, 233 x 185 mm, framed and glazed (frame was removed; only the wooden board of the photograph was kept with studio imprint on verso).
  - Photographic Portraits, undated; 1 folder (Folder 2)
    Includes thirteen albumen print photographs, carte de visite format, (105 x 63 mm) of William Powell Frith, William Holman Hunt, James Clarke Hook, Daniel Maclise (recto and verso with studio imprint of the stamp of the Victorian photography studio "Elliott & Fry, 55. Baker Street Portman Square, verso also with contemporary inscription in pencil); of Gustave Doré and Sir Edwin Henry Landseer (verso with studio imprint "John Watkins Photographer to the Queen, the Prince of Wales and the ex Royal Family of France. 34, Parliament Street, London S.W.," verso also with contemporary inscription in pencil); Sir John Everett Millais and William Linnell (verso with studio imprint: "Photographers to HRH the Prince of Wales. The London Stereoscopic and Photographic Company"); Otto von Bismarck (verso with studio imprint: "Numa Blank. Photographe de S.M.Le Roi de Prusse. 29, Boulevart des Italiens, Paris"); John Leech (verso with studio imprint "McLean and Haes Photographers and Miniature Painters, 26. Haymarket, London S.W."); and Sir John Everett Millais (verso with studio imprint: "Patronized by her Majesty Caldesi, Blanford and Co. Photographers, 13. Pall Mall East, London"). There is also a photographic portrait of Edward Lear; and one portrait (165 x 105 mm) probably of William Tipping (recto and verso with studio imprint: "Priestley and Sons. Egremont Cheshire."
- Series 5. Printed Material, 1833-1991; more than 10 folders
  This series consists of printed maps, brochures, journals, and books.
  This series has been arranged in a chronological order and by type of material.
  - The Bookman. London: Hodder and Stoughton., 1908 October; 1 folder (Folder 3)
  - Kent Between Sevenoaks and Westerham. The Beautiful Freehold and Residential Estate Known as Brasted Place, 1912; 2 folders (Folder 4-5)
    This is a final edition made by the direction of the Executor of the late colonel W. Fearon Tipping. Included also is a photocopy of the first edition.
  - Kent. The Freehold Residential Property Known as Brasted Place, 1918; 1 folder (Folder 6)
    At the back of the book there is a folded color plan of the Brasted place estates between Seven Oaks and Westerham Kent for sale by private treaty by Messrs. Knight, Frank and Rutley dated 1918.
  - Tipping, H. Avray. Old English Furniture: Its True Value and Function. London: Country Life Limited, 1928; 1 folder (Folder 7)
    Included also are some loose page notes.
  - Brasted Place Near Sevenoaks Kent, 1933; 1 folder (Folder 8)
  - Darwin, Bernard. Fifty Years of "Country Life." London: Country Life Limited, 1947; 1 folder (Folder 9)
  - Singleton, H.G.H. Brasted Place and Its Owners: A Short History, 1954; portion of 1 folder (Folder 10)
  - A Brief History of Stokenchurch and the Parish Church of SS. Peter and Paul, 1960; portion of 1 folder (Folder 10)
  - Ruskin and his Circle. [London, Arts Council, 1964] Arts Council Gallery, 17 January-15 February, 1964 January 17-February 15; portion of 1 folder (Folder 10)
  - Bygone Kent: A Monthly Journal of All Aspects of local history, 11 (12) and 12 (1), 1990-1991; 1 folder (Folder 11)
  - Tipping, H. Avray. The Story of Montacute and its house. London: Country Life Limited, undated; 1 folder (Folder 12)
  - Article: "H. Avray Tipping in Monmouthshire" by H.G. Singleton, undated; 1 folder (Folder 13)
- 32101080595232 (Box 1)
- 32101080595224 (Box 2)
- 32101080595216 (Box 3)
- 32101080595208 (Box 4)